<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Open Climate Fix]]></title><description><![CDATA[Open Climate Fix is a new non-profit research and development lab, totally focused on reducing greenhouse gas emissions as rapidly as possible. Every part of the organisation is designed to maximise climate impact, such as our open and collaborative approach, our rapid prototyping, and our attention on finding scalable & practical solutions.]]></description><link>https://openclimatefix.org</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 16:20:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Open Energy]]></title><description><![CDATA[Back in the 1980s, computers communicated over a hodge-podge mix of clunky, complex protocols. Building new services spanning more than one…]]></description><link>https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2020-06-15-open-energy/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2020-06-15-open-energy/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Back in the 1980s, computers communicated over a hodge-podge mix of clunky, complex protocols. Building new services spanning more than one machine (or just maintaining existing services) was painful, expensive and slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, in 1990, Tim Berners-Lee (now Sir Tim Berners-Lee) defined two elegant, open, standard protocols to allow computers to exchange rich, structured, linked data: the hypertext transfer protocol (the &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; at the start of URLs) and the hypertext markup language (&lt;code&gt;html&lt;/code&gt;: the code that defines how web pages are displayed and linked together).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;html&lt;/code&gt; enabled the world wide web, and gave rise to the previously unimaginable diversity of today&apos;s web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note what Tim Berners-Lee &lt;em&gt;didn&apos;t&lt;/em&gt; do: He &lt;em&gt;didn&apos;t&lt;/em&gt; build a proprietary platform. Nor did he force everyone else&apos;s content to go through a central system. Instead, he enabled millions of people to take complete ownership over their systems. But, crucially, these distributed systems communicate with ease because they speak the same language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the Energy system is ripe for the development of open standards for &lt;a href=&quot;https://icebreakerone.org/what-is-shared-data/&quot;&gt;sharing data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are facing the huge challenge of decarbonizing our electricity grid. The good news is that we&apos;re making amazing progress installing renewable generation and batteries, and flexing demand. But these millions of diverse, distributed systems must work together by communicating in the same language. That bad news is that, today, these systems speak wildly different languages, and so it&apos;s very hard for these systems to work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://es.catapult.org.uk/reports/energy-data-taskforce-report/&quot;&gt;Energy Data Taskforce report&lt;/a&gt; made a compelling case for why the energy system should share data: it will reduce costs, lower the barrier to entry for innovators, and - the bit that we at Open Climate Fix are most passionate about - help achieve net-zero emissions. And, last Friday, Ofgem &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.current-news.co.uk/news/ofgem-to-introduce-new-license-condition-for-presumed-open-data&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that they will introduce a new license condition for Presumed Open data, based on the Energy System Catapult&apos;s Data Best Practice guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdbb.cam.ac.uk/what-we-do/national-digital-twin-programme&quot;&gt;Centre for Digital Built Britain&apos;s National Digital Twin&lt;/a&gt; programme is designing a broad framework for describing physical infrastructure using distributed digital representations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all fantastic progress, and makes it clear &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; we must share energy data, and starts to sketch out &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to share data. But we need to get into the details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&apos;s needed now is for us, as a community, to define elegant, open standards to allow energy systems to share data whilst ensuring security, privacy and legal protection, and rewarding data owners for sharing their data.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, we need to decide on how to collaboratively evolve a vocabulary to describe energy assets; how to uniquely identify physical assets; how to express that - for example - only authorised users can access domestic meter data, but everyone can see data from the grid supply point from which that domestic meter is fed. And, crucially, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@agentGav/the-web-of-data-vs-the-web-of-pages-a560f3e73c21&quot;&gt;there are many non-technical problems to solve to enable this web of data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In creating these standards, we must remember that energy companies are already very busy doing a world-class job of keeping the lights on. So any new standard must be as simple to implement as possible. This is a great opportunity to remove complexity that exists only for historical reasons. What&apos;s really needed today? How can we make these standards as easy-to-use as possible, whilst significantly improving the system?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also make life easier by glueing together existing parts, rather than reinventing the wheel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we - as a community - get these standards right then, over the coming years and decades, open standards will transform everything in the energy system including network management; demand-side flexibility at scale; electric vehicle smart charging; energy forecasting; resource planning; decarbonisation of heating; community energy; research; policy; coordination of heat, power and transport; the list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the vision behind &lt;a href=&quot;https://icebreakerone.org/2020/06/01/open-energy/&quot;&gt;Open Energy&lt;/a&gt;, the project led by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dgen.net/0/overview/biog-gavin-starks/&quot;&gt;Gavin Starks&lt;/a&gt; (previously founding CEO of the Open Data Institute where he worked closely with Sir Tim Berners-Lee, and co-chair of the Open Banking Standard) &amp;#x26; his &lt;a href=&quot;https://icebreakerone.org/&quot;&gt;Icebreaker One&lt;/a&gt; non-profit in partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.passivsystems.com/&quot;&gt;PassivSystems&lt;/a&gt; (leaders in demand-side flexibility) and Open Climate Fix, and funded by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://apply-for-innovation-funding.service.gov.uk/competition/491/overview&quot;&gt;Modernising Energy Data Access Phase 1&lt;/a&gt; grant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are holding a series of webinars over the coming weeks to ask for your help - &lt;a href=&quot;https://icebreakerone.org/2020/06/01/open-energy/&quot;&gt;please register here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we really do need your help - none of us have been in charge of a control room when the frequency is drifting north; or had to take billion-pound decisions on where to build new infrastructure; or... ; you get the idea! This common language for energy must be laser-focused on solving real problems. We need your help!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s get started :)&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[What’s happening at Open Climate Fix? An Update.]]></title><description><![CDATA[There is certainly a lot going on in the world right now, and we hope everyone reading this blog post is in good health. While it is hard to…]]></description><link>https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2020-05-07-update/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2020-05-07-update/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;There is certainly a lot going on in the world right now, and we hope everyone reading this blog post is in good health. While it is hard to think about anything else right now, the challenge of climate change is no less urgent. We wanted to give an update on what&apos;s happening at Open Climate Fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it’s encouraging to see emissions going down in the short term, we are hoping to create a world where we can lock in those gains for the long term! Many things have happened here at Open Climate Fix since our last blog post, so here’s an update. Let’s look at the current status of our two big projects: Nowcasting and PV Mapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-we-work-on-these-projects-again&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-do-we-work-on-these-projects-again&quot; aria-label=&quot;why do we work on these projects again permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why do we work on these projects again?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with our two projects: They both directly work towards our current goal, which is to predict how much electricity will be produced by solar photovoltaic (PV) panels over the next few hours (called &quot;nowcasting&quot;). More about why we work on nowcasting can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://openclimatefix.org/projects/nowcasting&quot;&gt;on our project page&lt;/a&gt;. In short: Solar Photovoltaics are awesome, but it is hard to predict their power output. A big cloud will cause solar electricity generation to drop. That’s bad, because electricity supply must match demand at every moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To protect against drops in PV electricity generation (read: big clouds), electricity grid operators instruct some fossil-fuel generators to run below their maximum capacity. If PV generation drops, grid operators instruct these &quot;spinning reserve&quot; generators ramp up quickly to cover the lost PV generation. Supply and demand are kept in balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While “spinning reserve” sounds great at first, that usually means having a fleet of natural-gas turbines running at low efficiency (gas turbines are less fuel-efficient and carbon-efficient when throttled back). If we knew with greater certainty that there won’t be any big clouds in the next few hours and thus PV generation won’t go down, we could tell the grid operators to commit to a smaller number of generators, each running close to their maximum capacity; rather than committing to a large number of generators running below their maximum capacity and hence running at low efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/ec/Gas_Turbine_Blade.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blades of a Gas Turbine&quot;&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;A gas turbine that’s more than idle (Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Gas_Turbine_Blade.jpg&quot;&gt;Pro-Per Energy Services&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We estimate, conservatively, that better PV forecasts could reduce UK CO2 emissions by 100,000 tonnes CO2 per year (although this number is very hard to estimate with precision!). This estimate goes up to 100 million tonnes of CO2 globally by 2030. More about our assumptions and how we got to that estimate can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1sfBJ48_hxSEH-XFrwmH0leS4rSsrBKgwzfoeoqGRPfg/edit#heading=h.m4udy6vx0t7k&quot;&gt;our “original” OCF doc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;nowcasting-progress&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#nowcasting-progress&quot; aria-label=&quot;nowcasting progress permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Nowcasting progress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To predict PV generation for any point in the UK we made the following progress:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acquired and parsed tens of terabytes of satellite imagery &amp;#x26; PV data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial results from our own machine learning research indicates the approach is viable. More to come!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborated with amazing students on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://stanfordmlgroup.github.io/programs/aicc-bootcamp/&quot;&gt;Stanford AI for Climate Change Bootcamp&lt;/a&gt; where 3 Stanford students worked on solar PV Nowcasting for 6 months. Their results are very promising!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Established with stakeholders that the nowcast fills a gap in current knowledge, and we will continue to interview potential users of nowcasting to better understand their needs (and this research will be published!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have ongoing collaborations with two more awesome students!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the near future, we hope to release a public dataset of satellite imagery &amp;#x26; PV data, and run a public ML competition on Nowcasting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;https://openclimatefix.org/projects/nowcasting&quot;&gt;Read more about Nowcasting&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pv-mapping&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#pv-mapping&quot; aria-label=&quot;pv mapping permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;PV Mapping&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To estimate how much photovoltaic energy will be produced, we first need to know where the PV systems are. At the moment this is not well known in the UK for all but the largest PV systems - particularly domestic systems are poorly documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the progress we made with the PV mapping project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We supported &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/UK_2019_Q3_Project:_Solar_Power&quot;&gt;a project on OpenStreetMap to map solar PV systems&lt;/a&gt;. Volunteers mapped 100,000 new PV systems in the UK in just 3-months, &amp;#x26; continue to add PV systems to OSM. We were blown away! Huge thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mcld.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Dan Stowell&lt;/a&gt; for leading this project!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We recently finished a 3-month project with partners at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.turing.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;Alan Turing Institute&lt;/a&gt;, Sheffield University, and Queen Mary University which developed code to combine several public UK PV maps into a single map. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/alan-turing-institute/solar-panel-detection&quot;&gt;The code is public&lt;/a&gt; and we plan to publish a &apos;merged&apos; PV map soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We supported a 2019 UCL MSc research project on using machine learning to detect solar domestic PV systems in aerial imagery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a next step we are looking into running a public ML competition on locating solar PV systems in aerial imagery soon, and to continue working on merging existing databases of solar PV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-07-09-solar-pv-mapping&quot;&gt;Read more about PV Mapping&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;announcing-our-co-funding-award-with-the-european-space-agency-esa&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#announcing-our-co-funding-award-with-the-european-space-agency-esa&quot; aria-label=&quot;announcing our co funding award with the european space agency esa permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Announcing our Co-Funding Award with the European Space Agency (ESA)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One progress update we didn’t mention yet for Nowcasting is actually quite a big one: We got funding from the European Space Agency! As you might have seen on Twitter, the ESA has awarded us an AI Kick-Start co-funding for six months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;We’re over the moon that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/esa?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@ESA&lt;/a&gt; has awarded us an AI Kick-Start co-funding for six months! 🚀&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Kick-Start activities are compact Feasability Studies to explore new service concepts that use space tech.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Our research will be public, of course! 😉 &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ESAbusinessapps?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@ESAbusinessapps&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Space4Europe?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Space4Europe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Open Climate Fix (@OpenClimateFix) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/OpenClimateFix/status/1247162475738529797?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 6, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is awesome news and will definitely help us accelerate working on Nowcasting. We will be reaching out to various partners and potential users of Nowcasting and interview them on their needs and wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#conclusion&quot; aria-label=&quot;conclusion permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite everything going on in the world right now, we are still positive and are continuing to work on fixing the climate. We talked to so many people over the last couple of months, open sourced &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/openclimatefix&quot;&gt;seven different GitHub repositories&lt;/a&gt; and started Nowcasting and PV Mapping as projects. We already took a lot of steps and got awarded our first co-funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you &lt;a href=&quot;https://openclimatefix.us20.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=ceb017fe32f0a4620227fda8a&amp;#x26;id=d56fc32a31&quot;&gt;subscribe to our newsletter&lt;/a&gt; if you want to stay up to date. We even have an &lt;a href=&quot;https://openclimatefix.org/rss.xml&quot;&gt;RSS feed&lt;/a&gt; for our blog now, thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/openclimatefix/website/pull/46&quot;&gt;Grant (@grantbdev) on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. We will be picking up blogging more actively again, so definitely stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So long!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Using computing to fix climate change]]></title><description><![CDATA[If you'd like to use computer science to help mitigate climate change, then check out these resources: ClimateChange.AI - All about using AI…]]></description><link>https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-10-03-using-computing-to-fix-climate-change/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-10-03-using-computing-to-fix-climate-change/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;d like to use computer science to help mitigate climate change, then check out these resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://climatechange.ai/&quot;&gt;ClimateChange.AI&lt;/a&gt; - All about using AI to mitigate and adapt to climate change. Check out their excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.05433&quot;&gt;2019 paper&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.climatechange.ai/mailing_list.html&quot;&gt;sign up&lt;/a&gt; to their newsletter! Also check out Paul Strobel&apos;s six-part illustrated &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.codecentric.de/en/2019/09/how-to-tackle-climate-change-with-machine-learning-electricity-systems/#post-69396&quot;&gt;blog series&lt;/a&gt; about the paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://openclimatefix.org&quot;&gt;Open Climate Fix&lt;/a&gt; - OCF is the non-profit that I co-founded. Entirely focused on using open science (especially machine learning) to mitigate climate change. Please &lt;a href=&quot;https://eepurl.com/guCjvH&quot;&gt;sign up&lt;/a&gt; to our newsletter and consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://airtable.com/shrl59GJ96csVF4WB&quot;&gt;adding your name to our list of volunteers&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mattermore.io/&quot;&gt;Matter More&lt;/a&gt; - &apos;Use your superpowers in AI and data science to reverse climate change - Discover exciting new initiatives and work opportunities.&apos;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sliced.org/&quot;&gt;Sliced&lt;/a&gt; - &apos;We help you find opportunities that have a direct impact on reversing climate change.&apos;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://climateaction.tech/&quot;&gt;ClimateAction.Tech&lt;/a&gt; - &apos;A global community of tech professionals using our skills, expertise and platforms to support solutions to the climate crisis.&apos;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://worrydream.com/ClimateChange/#&quot;&gt;Bret Victor&apos;s blog: What can a technologist do about climate change - 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dynamicallytyped.com/&quot;&gt;Dynamically Typed newsletter&lt;/a&gt; - bi-weekly newsletter about AI-powered products and ML research that also features new projects and resources for using AI to tackle the climate crisis in every edition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you know of other resources, then please add a comment below or, even better, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/JackKelly/JackKelly.github.io/blob/master/_posts/2019-10-03-using-computing-to-fix-climate-change.md&quot;&gt;submit a pull request&lt;/a&gt; to improve this list!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-challenge-of-reducing-emissions-at-scale&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-challenge-of-reducing-emissions-at-scale&quot; aria-label=&quot;the challenge of reducing emissions at scale permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The challenge of reducing emissions at scale&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One quick rant: All the climate cares about is the scale of emissions reductions. For the climate to &apos;notice&apos;, we need to reduce emissions by &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; a million tonnes of CO2e per year, and ideally &lt;em&gt;billions&lt;/em&gt; of tonnes per year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve scale we need to jump over multiple hurdles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a great research idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk to industry to check that your idea solves a real problem. (I don&apos;t know about you, but I find it all to easy to fixate on solving &apos;toy&apos; problems. It&apos;s essential that we focus on solving &apos;real&apos; problems.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a proof-of-concept that demonstrates emission reductions in a controlled environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a product (or get your idea implemented into an existing product) that reduces emissions &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; solves problems that industry cares about, at a price they can afford, and in a way which fits easily into their existing systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persuade industry to adopt the product / idea. (Marketing, support, iterating on the product after receiving critical feedback, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become financially sustainable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduce emissions! (Even if you succeed at all the previous steps, that&apos;s no guarantee that you&apos;ll reduce emissions at scale. Maybe there&apos;s a rebound effect? Maybe there are some other unintended consequences?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects tend to attract most funding and media attention after completing a proof-of-concept. But we need to get all the way to the final step before we can be confident that a given intervention will actually reduce emissions at scale. The systems that we&apos;re trying to change (such as the energy system) are enormously complex. Demonstrating success in a small research setting does not guarantee success at scale (unfortunately!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck! It&apos;s gonna be tough. But we can&apos;t fail. To paraphrase Greta: If we fail, future generations will never forgive us. (Sorry to be so gloomy!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&apos;s also technically exciting work (and actually quite good fun!) and there&apos;s a great community of people using computer science to mitigate climate change! So, dive in - we need your help!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Starting work on solar PV mapping]]></title><description><![CDATA[Solar PV mapping is a sub-project of our PV nowcasting project. Nowcasting will provide solar PV yield predictions for any location. To be…]]></description><link>https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-07-09-solar-pv-mapping/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-07-09-solar-pv-mapping/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Solar PV mapping is a sub-project of our &lt;a href=&quot;http://jack-kelly.com/blog/2019-07-01-starting-solar-electricity-nowcasting&quot;&gt;PV nowcasting project&lt;/a&gt;. Nowcasting will provide solar PV yield predictions for any location. To be able to arrive at an accurate forecast for solar power generation (out-turn), we need to know where all the PV panels are!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The OpenStreetMap (OSM) community has already done an incredible job mapping over 10,000 PV installations in the UK (out of over 1 million we believe to exist) and many more across the world. Our goal is to help grow the effort and drastically increase the amount of PV mapped in OSM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent research (&lt;a href=&quot;http://web.stanford.edu/group/deepsolar/home&quot;&gt;DeepSolar&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1902.10895.pdf&quot;&gt;SolarMapper from DUKE&lt;/a&gt; are just two examples) has shown the power of machine learning (ML) for identifying PV panels in satellite and aerial imagery at scale. We want to make it easy for anyone to start using ML to map PV across the world, and help pull together the datasets that are generated into a global open database (which can be used for updating OSM).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By creating a comprehensive open database of PV installations, we think that many other people will find interesting ways to use the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK is our initial focus for the nowcasting project, so we have also focused on mapping PV installations there initially. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LaurenceWWatson&quot;&gt;Laurence Watson&lt;/a&gt; has taken up the challenge of mapping UK PV using high-resolution 25cm aerial imagery. Although licensing does not allow the aerial imagery to be shared, we will be open sourcing the methods and tools we use. We are using the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://rastervision.io/&quot;&gt;Raster Vision&lt;/a&gt; framework, which will make it easier for anyone to reuse and contribute to the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in doing a similar ML mapping project in your country (where we can find high resolution imagery), please reach out, as we will be happy to collaborate whilst we do the UK project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other groups doing similar PV mapping projects, and we are excited about the prospect of growing the community, and providing a place for these PV datasets to live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-can-you-contribute&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-can-you-contribute&quot; aria-label=&quot;how can you contribute permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How can you contribute?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Map PV installations manually from street level or satellite imagery directly in OSM. There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Renewable_energy_in_the_United_Kingdom/Rooftop_Solar_PV&quot;&gt;more details on the OSM wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help us clean and organise PV location data. Could involve GIS work or building software to automate things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contribute to existing ML PV mapping projects. There is lots of work to be done improving accuracy of the models. Projects include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UK small scale PV by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LaurenceWWatson&quot;&gt;Laurence Watson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tyler Busby is mapping PV in the USA using Mapbox satellite imagery: &lt;a href=&quot;http://openclimatefix.discourse.group/t/solarpaneldatawrangler/26&quot;&gt;SolarPanelDataWrangler&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start a new project to map small (residential and business) PV installations in your (or any) country.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a specific area of PV mapping you&apos;d like to get involved in, feel free to reach out to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dctanner&quot;&gt;@dctanner&lt;/a&gt;. Or more generally, if you’d like to get involved, please register your interest on &lt;a href=&quot;https://airtable.com/shrl59GJ96csVF4WB&quot;&gt;OCF’s volunteer register&lt;/a&gt; and/or join the conversations on &lt;a href=&quot;http://openclimatefix.discourse.group/&quot;&gt;OCF’s forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Starting work on solar electricity nowcasting]]></title><description><![CDATA[At Open Climate Fix, we're about to start work on our solar electricity (PV) nowcasting project. The aim of this project is to help reduce…]]></description><link>https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-07-01-starting-solar-electricity-nowcasting/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-07-01-starting-solar-electricity-nowcasting/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;http://openclimatefix.org&quot;&gt;Open Climate Fix&lt;/a&gt;, we&apos;re about to start work on our solar electricity (PV) nowcasting project. The aim of this project is to help reduce emissions (and costs) by forecasting solar electricity power production at high temporal and spatial resolution, but with a forecast time horizon of a few hours. We&apos;ll use machine learning to combine satellite images, numerical weather predictions, and live solar PV data. All our research code will be open source; and we&apos;ll blog about our results (including negative results); and we&apos;re working hard to make it easy for other researchers to access the data necessary to do this research :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be kept up to date, please &lt;a href=&quot;https://eepurl.com/guCjvH&quot;&gt;sign up to OCF&apos;s newsletter&lt;/a&gt; (and/or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jack_kelly&quot;&gt;follow Jack on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!). If you&apos;d like to get involved, please register your interest on &lt;a href=&quot;https://airtable.com/shrl59GJ96csVF4WB&quot;&gt;OCF&apos;s volunteer register&lt;/a&gt; and/or join the conversations on &lt;a href=&quot;http://openclimatefix.discourse.group/&quot;&gt;OCF&apos;s forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCF is also working on mapping the location of PV panels. We&apos;ll blog about the PV mapping project soon :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-solar-electricity-nowcasting-useful&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-is-solar-electricity-nowcasting-useful&quot; aria-label=&quot;why is solar electricity nowcasting useful permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why is solar electricity nowcasting useful?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several uses for better solar forecasts. One use case that we&apos;re focusing on is to help electricity system operators (like the UK National Grid) to schedule spinning reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does that mean?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The physics of the electricity grid dictate that, at every moment, supply must exactly match demand. Small changes in demand are handled automatically: When you turn on your kettle, a generator somewhere on the grid will automatically produce a tiny bit more power. But what if a large cloud covers hundreds of megawatts of solar PV panels? The lost PV generation must be replaced within a few seconds. But it takes many minutes, or even hours, to spin up a natural-gas power plant from cold. So, whenever any solar PV power is on the system, electricity system operators schedule lots of &apos;upwards spinning reserve&apos; (typically thermal generators which are operated at less than 100% capacity, and so can be ramped up quickly to replace lost PV generation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, system operators take a fairly crude and conservative approach to deciding how much spinning reserve to schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With better forecasts for solar PV generation, electricity system operators will be able to schedule spinning reserve more efficiently, which will reduce emissions from the spinning reserve, and reduce costs, and enable the electricity system to handle a greater penetration of solar PV. In particular, we need solar PV nowcasts which do a good job of quantifying &lt;em&gt;uncertainty&lt;/em&gt;. If we&apos;re confident the day will stay sunny, we can schedule less spinning reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our aims is to run a pilot project with at least one electricity system operator, to test if probabilistic PV nowcasts really do help schedule the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conventional-forecasting-techniques-arent-well-suited-for-solar-nowcasting&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#conventional-forecasting-techniques-arent-well-suited-for-solar-nowcasting&quot; aria-label=&quot;conventional forecasting techniques arent well suited for solar nowcasting permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Conventional forecasting techniques aren&apos;t well suited for solar nowcasting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conventional forecasting techniques (&apos;numerical weather predictions&apos;) are fantastic at forecasting things like the temperature and wind speeds for tomorrow. But numerical weather predictions aren&apos;t so good at forecasting the amount of sunlight falling on the Earth&apos;s surface (&apos;irradiance&apos;), nor are they great at predicting the next few hours (&apos;nowcasting&apos;). This is for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numerical weather models take at least an hour to run and so, by the time they&apos;ve finished executing, they are already an hour out of date with respect to the most recent observations. This isn&apos;t a problem for forecasting temperature. But clouds can change quite dramatically over an hour!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solar irradiance is greatly affected by clouds; yet operational numerical weather models can&apos;t resolve clouds. Instead, numerical weather models &apos;parameterise&apos; clouds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &apos;radiative transfer codes&apos; in numerical weather models (the bits which simulate light bouncing around the atmosphere) are some of the most computationally expensive bits of numerical weather models, and so might be run infrequently, or might be run in quite a limited fashion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historically, there simply hasn&apos;t been much demand for highly accurate forecasts for irradiance. And so not much research has been done on the topic (although that is changing: We&apos;re certainly not the only folks working on solar PV nowcasting!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-planned-approach&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#our-planned-approach&quot; aria-label=&quot;our planned approach permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Our planned approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&apos;ll explore if machine learning (ML) can help nowcast solar PV power production. There&apos;s quite a lot of data available to train ML models; and there are lots of ML engineers who are keen to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, we&apos;re planning to work on several distinct ML tasks. In brief, we plan to split the problem into two parts: nowcast the movement of clouds; and then infer solar PV power for a given configuration of the atmosphere. In a little more detail, the steps are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Infer solar PV yield (normalised by clear-sky PV yield) from satellite images of clouds, and numerical weather predictions. That is, don&apos;t forecast the &lt;em&gt;future&lt;/em&gt;, &apos;just&apos; try to learn the &apos;radiative transfer function&apos; of the atmosphere. Learn how different types of clouds and aerosols affect the passage of sunlight through the atmosphere. If this works, then we&apos;ll end up with a system which can tell us the solar PV yield for a single site, given a satellite image of cloud cover over that site, and maybe some data about aerosols, ozone, and water vapour. We can &apos;sweep&apos; this model across large geographical areas to produce a historical &apos;solar PV reanalysis&apos; dataset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn how clouds move. We&apos;ll start simple, and use conventional &apos;nowcasting&apos; techniques (Take the most recent satellite image of cloud cover. For each pixel of cloud, move that pixel according to the wind speed and direction at that pixel). Then we&apos;ll try modelling different vertical cloud decks separately (so if high cloud moves over lower cloud, our model should understand that the low cloud probably still exists, even though it&apos;s obscured by the higher cloud). Finally, we&apos;ll try &apos;pure ML&apos; approaches (such as video prediction).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we&apos;ve built a proof-of-concept models for step 1 and 2, we&apos;ll combine these to produce a simple PV nowcasting system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clouds don&apos;t just &lt;em&gt;move&lt;/em&gt;. Clouds condense out of &apos;nothing&apos;; and evaporate / precipitate away into &apos;nothing&apos;. Clouds change shape; grow vertically; merge; split; change opacity, etc. Can we train a machine learning model to predict how clouds will &apos;evolve&apos; over a few hours?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more detailed plan is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1IS0h-W_GyRRUDV8Ur1jiWXYSGZn_Soq-H0UUdvmpXi0/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ultra-open-science-and-how-to-get-involved&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ultra-open-science-and-how-to-get-involved&quot; aria-label=&quot;ultra open science and how to get involved permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ultra-open science; and how to get involved&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All our code will be open (on GitHub); we&apos;ll blog about results (including negative results); we&apos;ll openly discuss ideas and concerns; and we&apos;ll maintain a public &apos;leaderboard&apos; to show how well different models have performed (hopefully, over time, many of those models will be built by other people!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;ll take us another few months to get the project off the ground but, once we do, we&apos;d love people to get involved in the conversations; and to build software tools to help process and visualise the data :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, by far the best way to scale this research across multiple people is probably to enable you folks to try your own modelling approaches (i.e. to take Open Climate Fix out of the loop! You guys just download the data, and maybe use some open-source tools the community develops, and try to beat the current state-of-the-art, and then send your score to the leaderboard)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we write a paper, then everyone who contributes ideas or code will be listed as an author :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;d like to get involved, please register your interest on &lt;a href=&quot;https://airtable.com/shrl59GJ96csVF4WB&quot;&gt;OCF&apos;s volunteer register&lt;/a&gt; and/or join the conversations on &lt;a href=&quot;http://openclimatefix.discourse.group/&quot;&gt;OCF&apos;s forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;data&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#data&quot; aria-label=&quot;data permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we started Open Climate Fix, we hoped to be able to make life super-easy for researchers by collating all relevant datasets into one location. Unfortunately, we&apos;re strictly not allowed to &apos;redistribute&apos; the satellite data, so we can&apos;t collate the satellite data. We&apos;re working on fixing this! But this isn&apos;t a deal-breaker, as each individual researcher can download the historical satellite data for free from the satellite data provider (EUMETSAT). We&apos;ll try to make tools and documentation to make this as painless as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&apos;re also working hard to get some solar PV power data released into the open.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to get involved with Open Climate Fix]]></title><description><![CDATA[I'm building a non-profit called Open Climate Fix, entirely focused on using open-science to help fix climate change ASAP. We'd love help…]]></description><link>https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-03-06-how-to-get-involved/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-03-06-how-to-get-involved/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m building a non-profit called &lt;a href=&quot;http://openclimatefix.org&quot;&gt;Open Climate Fix&lt;/a&gt;, entirely focused on using open-science to help fix climate change ASAP. We&apos;d love help :) This blog post lists a few concrete things we need help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a quick disclaimer: OCF is still very, &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; young. &lt;del&gt;We don&apos;t yet have funding, a bank account, or an online forum. (These things will come!)&lt;/del&gt; I&apos;m spending the majority of my time meeting people (I&apos;ve had over 100 meetings over the last 7 weeks, and plenty more planned - I&apos;m trying hard to focus on meetings relevant to solar PV now). So, please be patient with me! Once I actually start writing code and releasing data, then there will be much more for folks to get stuck into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, here are a few ideas for how to help!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Please take a look at our list of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1tk9cF4O539TzaMaUufn9Ay4f6qKKEyoNKmzP03kbSDo/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Solar data &amp;#x26; software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and add any resources that you can find! e.g. we&apos;d love help locating more sources of satellite data of cloud cover.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/14UZd_qdAjD8P1VGNQThf3rZz9tBCXk2_ySZ_oNIEdSs/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Solar Projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; doc. Please comment on any projects that you&apos;d like to help with. Heck, if you want, please go right ahead and take the lead on any of those projects :) For example, one great stand-alone project would be to build a simple website to allow people to enter the location of PV panels into Open Street Map. (Please comment on the doc if you do go ahead and start work on a project, so we don&apos;t duplicate work.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Solar Projects doc includes some &apos;research&apos; sections. These sections contain lists of ideas for self-contained &lt;strong&gt;research projects&lt;/strong&gt;, many of which don&apos;t require any coding (just spending some time googling stuff and/or contacting people). We&apos;d people to take on these research projects!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please help with &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://openclimatefix.org&quot;&gt;openclimatefix.org&lt;/a&gt; website&lt;/strong&gt;! (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/openclimatefix/openclimatefix.github.io/&quot;&gt;Code is on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;). Feel free to submit pull requests for small changes. For big changes, please describe your proposal in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/openclimatefix/openclimatefix.github.io/issues&quot;&gt;the issue queue&lt;/a&gt; before you start coding, just to make sure no one else is already working on something similar! I&apos;m working on some more content, but I&apos;d love help making that content look good :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;We also need a &lt;strong&gt;logo&lt;/strong&gt; :)&lt;/del&gt; [&lt;strong&gt;edit.&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;%5BLINKEDIN%5D(https://www.linkedin.com/in/harryolson/)&quot;&gt;Harry Olson&lt;/a&gt; we now have a wonderful logo. Check out his website here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://haocreative.ca&quot;&gt;https://haocreative.ca&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join &lt;a href=&quot;http://openclimatefix.discourse.group&quot;&gt;the OCF web discussion forum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data!&lt;/strong&gt; Do you work at an organisation with solar PV power timeseries data or PV location data or satellite imagery? (e.g. an inverter company, or a solar analytics company)? Or do you know someone who does?! If so, &lt;em&gt;please&lt;/em&gt; get in touch. I&apos;m very hungry for good PV data!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have PV power data, please either email it to me (jack@OpenClimateFix.org), or upload the power data to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pvoutput.org/&quot;&gt;PVOutput.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Map the geographical location of PV systems in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openstreetmap.org&quot;&gt;Open Street Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Tag:generator:source=solar&quot;&gt;tag:generator:source=solar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Domain expertise!&lt;/strong&gt; If you know about cloud forecasting / aerosol forecasting / determining the toplogy of the electricity network / related things then please email me (jack@openclimatefix.org)!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Erm... it&apos;s always awkward talking about &lt;strong&gt;money&lt;/strong&gt; but, um, if you are into climate philanthropy - or if you know of anyone who&apos;s into climate philanthropy - then please email us (info@openclimatefix.org)! My intention is that Open Climate Fix will reduce emissions by millions of tonnes (at least), at a cost of a few dollars per tonne. (i.e. considerably cheaper than most other interventions).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Solar PV nowcasting]]></title><description><![CDATA[Solar PV is the single biggest source of uncertainty in the National Grid's forecasts. To mitigate against the risk of a large cloud…]]></description><link>https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-01-09-solar-PV-nowcasting/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-01-09-solar-PV-nowcasting/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Solar PV is the single biggest source of uncertainty in the National Grid&apos;s forecasts. To mitigate against the risk of a large cloud sweeping across the country (and hence the grid losing gigawatts of PV generation), the National Grid keep lots of natural gas generators idling (&apos;spinning reserve&apos;). These gas turbines are kept idling because they take several hours to start up from cold, but they can be ramped up very quickly from idle; and the physics of the grid dictate that - at every instant - supply must precisely match demand. So, any loss in PV supply must be immediately replaced. Spinning reserve costs a lot of money and pumps out a lot of CO2. If the National Grid had better PV forecasts, even for the next few hours, they could reduce the amount of spinning reserve required, and hence reduce emissions (by about 100,000 tonnes per year) and reduce costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Nowcasting&quot; is a bit of an odd term. It means &quot;forecasting for the next few hours&quot;. In general, &quot;nowcasting&quot; doesn&apos;t use the hugely complex and expensive numerical weather models that run on super computers and constitute the bread-and-butter for most forecasting agencies. Instead, &quot;nowcasting&quot; usually uses statistical techniques to take recent observations and &apos;roll them forwards&apos;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that most nowcasting research up until now has been done on rainfall (because predicting floods saves lives). Relatively little research has been done on nowcasting sunlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m a machine learning researcher. So, my main interest is in trying to build machine learning models to nowcast solar PV (which basically boils down to trying to predict the movement and evolution of clouds). I&apos;d like to spend the majority of the next year or two writing code to experiment with new ways to predict sunlight for the next few hours. Inputs to the model may include satellite images of clouds, numerical weather predictions, vertical cloud profiles, and geographical information. As quickly as possible, I&apos;d like to get prototype PV nowcasts displayed in the National Grid control room, so we can start measuring the impact on emissions and cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I and my co-conspiriators got our heads round the datasets, we&apos;d love to create an open dataset, so that &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; can try their hand at beating the state-of-the-art in PV nowcasting :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt; Please see &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019-07-01-starting-solar-electricity-nowcasting&quot;&gt;July 2019&apos;s blog post&lt;/a&gt; for more details about PV nowcasting.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Update & FAQ on non-profit research lab]]></title><description><![CDATA[Two days ago I tweeted a link to a blog post I wrote stating that I'd left DeepMind to start a non-profit research lab, focused on reducing…]]></description><link>https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-01-09-update/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-01-09-update/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Two days ago I &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jack_kelly/status/1082283333202128897&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; a link to &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019-01-07-non-profit&quot;&gt;a blog post I wrote&lt;/a&gt; stating that I&apos;d left DeepMind to start a non-profit research lab, focused on reducing greenhouse gas emissions. I&apos;ve been absolutely blown away by the response! I was expecting maybe a couple of re-tweets. At the time of writing, the tweet has been retweeted 470 times, liked 2.1 thousand times, and I&apos;ve had over 200 messages! To be entirely honest, I&apos;m slightly overwhelmed! (in a good way!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;d like to answer some of the great questions that people have asked over the last few days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-stage-are-you-at&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-stage-are-you-at&quot; aria-label=&quot;what stage are you at permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What stage are you at?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m at the &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; beginning of setting up this non-profit! I haven&apos;t settled on a name or precise company structure, I don&apos;t have a website or office, and don&apos;t yet have any funding secured!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have some friends with whom I&apos;ve been discussion this non-profit for the last few months; some of these friends might get involved in the non-profit, although nothing is set-in-stone yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve also been talking to the UK Met Office and National Grid for a little while, and - although nothing is certain yet - it looks very likely that my first project will be forecasting PV in collaboration with the UK Met Office and National Grid. I&apos;m convinced that solar PV forecasting is likely to have significant climate impact, and it&apos;s a good fit for my skills and interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-you-have-a-mailing-list&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#do-you-have-a-mailing-list&quot; aria-label=&quot;do you have a mailing list permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Do you have a mailing list?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not yet! But I will set one up ASAP. In the mean time, please keep an eye on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jack_kelly&quot;&gt;my twitter feed&lt;/a&gt; :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-are-you-based&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#where-are-you-based&quot; aria-label=&quot;where are you based permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Where are you based?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peckham, London, UK :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tell-me-more-about-this-solar-pv-nowcasting-project&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tell-me-more-about-this-solar-pv-nowcasting-project&quot; aria-label=&quot;tell me more about this solar pv nowcasting project permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tell me more about this solar PV nowcasting project.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK! Please see &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019-01-09-solar-pv-nowcasting&quot;&gt;the Solar PV nowcasting blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;funding&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#funding&quot; aria-label=&quot;funding permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Funding?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t have funding yet but I plan to apply to the Network Innovation Allowance soon. This will provide enough money for my time and some compute resources for a year or two; but the NIA unlikely to provide enough money to employ anyone else for the first year or so, I&apos;m afraid - sorry!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;id-love-to-help&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#id-love-to-help&quot; aria-label=&quot;id love to help permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I&apos;d love to help!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amazing response to my tweet made it pretty clear that there are loads (thousands?) of highly skilled folks out there who are really keen to help fix climate change. This is fantastic news!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the solar PV nowcasting project, I&apos;d love to talk to anyone who has an interest in PV, machine learning (especially video prediction), battery scheduling, grid optimisation, and weather forecasting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll probably spend most of January &apos;just&apos; talking to people :) (That&apos;s what you&apos;re supposed to do at the start of a startup, right?!?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least until the end of January, I doubt I&apos;ll get any significant code written. But, once I do start writing code, I&apos;d love people to critique my preliminary results, and help bounce ideas around. I&apos;ll blog regularly with results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;pv-nowcasting-dataset-enable-anyone-to-try-to-beat-the-state-of-the-art-in-pv-nowcasting&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#pv-nowcasting-dataset-enable-anyone-to-try-to-beat-the-state-of-the-art-in-pv-nowcasting&quot; aria-label=&quot;pv nowcasting dataset enable anyone to try to beat the state of the art in pv nowcasting permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;PV nowcasting dataset: Enable anyone to try to beat the state-of-the-art in PV nowcasting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the medium term, we plan to put together a dataset and tool chain so &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; can try their hand at PV nowcasting. This is really important to me: I want to enable everyone from teenage ML hot-shots to multi-national corporations to try to improve on the state-of-the-art for PV nowcasting. If they succeed in beating the state-of-the-art then I&apos;d like to help get that algorithm into production so it can start making the world better ASAP :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-connect-skilled-people-with-projects-which-need-help&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-to-connect-skilled-people-with-projects-which-need-help&quot; aria-label=&quot;how to connect skilled people with projects which need help permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How to connect skilled people with projects which need help?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I probably won&apos;t be able to provide meaningful projects for the majority of people who very kindly reached out to me. Which raises the question: How best to allow this awesome group of people to get stuck into helping build stuff which helps to fix climate change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would a database of climate mitigation projects be useful? If you&apos;re looking to work on a project (either paid or unpaid), then you&apos;d look through this database to see if anything takes your fancy. If you&apos;re involved in a project, then you could ask for help. The emphasis would be on open-source projects which help to reduce emissions; but perhaps we&apos;d also allow closed-source projects to advertise? Does that sound useful? If so, would a newsletter be best? Or a blog, which perhaps also publishes interviews etc. with people involved in climate change mitigation? Or a listing on github? Or a forum? Or all of the above? Or does this already exist?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;scaling-up-the-research-lab&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#scaling-up-the-research-lab&quot; aria-label=&quot;scaling up the research lab permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Scaling up the research lab&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first year or two, I&apos;d like to focus mostly on solar PV nowcasting; and I&apos;d like to deliberately keep the lab quite small, so that we can be experimental and agile without jeopardising lots of peoples&apos; jobs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the solar PV nowcasting project goes well, and if the open-source approach has proved useful, then I&apos;d like to scale up to a few other projects. This is when the lab would start raising significant amounts of money and employing people to work on a range of projects (all open source; all laser-focused on fixing climate change at scale).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;press&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#press&quot; aria-label=&quot;press permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Press&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;d like to hold off on any press coverage at least for the next few weeks, please! I&apos;d at least like to have settled on a name and set up a mailing list before any articles are published!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I&apos;d feel much more comfortable waiting until this lab has actually had real-world impact before doing any significant publicity. All I&apos;ve done so far is write some blog posts and had a few meetings - stuff that the climate totally doesn&apos;t care about!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Starting a non-profit research lab to help fix climate change ASAP]]></title><description><![CDATA[I left Google DeepMind. This is a particularly odd decision because I love the team I worked with at DeepMind. Since joining DeepMind, I've…]]></description><link>https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-01-07-non-profit/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://openclimatefix.org/blog/2019-01-07-non-profit/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I left Google DeepMind. This is a particularly odd decision because I love the team I worked with at DeepMind. Since joining DeepMind, I&apos;ve been constantly amazed by this team&apos;s compassion, focus, intelligence, optimism, and desire for real-world impact. I&apos;ve learnt a huge amount from DeepMind, and I will miss this team dearly. Leaving this awesome team is enormously difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why did I leave?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m terrified by climate change; and I&apos;m increasingly convinced that climate change mitigation is a &apos;&lt;em&gt;go big or go home&lt;/em&gt;&apos; thing. I have two ideas for how to help. These ideas might be wrong. But I want to give them a shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first idea is motivated by the observation that some business norms (like hoarding intellectual property) get in the way of achieving climate impact. My hope is that it&apos;s possible to design an organisation which is optimised through-and-through for climate impact; and short-circuits all business norms which get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I will build &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1sfBJ48_hxSEH-XFrwmH0leS4rSsrBKgwzfoeoqGRPfg/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;a non-profit product development lab&lt;/a&gt;, obsessively focused on building things which reduce CO&lt;sub&gt;2e&lt;/sub&gt; emissions by at least one million tonnes per year; and hopefully &lt;em&gt;billions&lt;/em&gt; of tonnes per year. The aim is to catalyse systemic change and help the entire community (including DeepMind!) to have as much climate impact as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&apos;ll be very collaborative; everything will be open source; and we&apos;ll encourage others to commercialise our work and/or out-perform any systems we build. We&apos;ll aim for maximum CO&lt;sub&gt;2e&lt;/sub&gt; reduction per dollar. The non-profit will combine ideas from open-science and startup culture, and will focus on interventions which are practical and scalable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea is probably wildly naive. But I want to test it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second idea is the first project that the non-profit will work on: forecasting solar PV power production a few hours ahead by using machine learning to combine real-time satellite data with numerical weather predictions, in collaboration with the UK Met Office and National Grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don&apos;t interpret my resignation as a comment on DeepMind&apos;s likely climate impact. We all need DeepMind to have huge climate impact. And, if anyone can have impact, it&apos;s the astounding folks in DeepMind. Heck, they already &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepmind.com/blog/safety-first-ai-autonomous-data-centre-cooling-and-industrial-control/&quot;&gt;are having impact&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m extremely excited to start this non-profit; and can&apos;t wait to start building things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll post progress updates to twitter and my blog. Please feel free to email me at jack@OpenClimateFix.org if you&apos;d like more info. I probably won&apos;t get much coding done in January - Jan will mostly be spent setting up the non-profit, building a website etc. And settling on a name!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;UPDATE&lt;/em&gt;
Please see these blog posts for more info:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019-01-09-update&quot;&gt;Update on non-profit research lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019-01-09-solar-PV-nowcasting&quot;&gt;Solar PV nowcasting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>